Guide to the Hermina Dumont Huiswoud Papers and Photographs TAM.354
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Hermina Dumont Huiswoud Papers and Photographs
1890-1996
1928-1996
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Huiswoud, Hermina Dumont
Turner, Joyce Moore, 1920-
TAM.354
1.25 Linear Feet in 1 record carton and 5 folders.
Hermina ("Hermie") Dumont Huiswoud (1905-1998), was born in British Guiana (now Guyana), and migrated to New York in 1919. In 1926 she married Otto Eduard Huiswoud (1893-1961), born in Dutch Guiana (now Surinam) and a charter member of the Communist Party of the United States of America, with whom Hermina was also active in international communist activities, eventually settling in Amsterdam in 1949. The collection contains correspondence and a manuscript regarding Otto Huiswoud, letters from Langston Hughes, published and unpublished writings, personalia, and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Joyce Moore Turner in 2006. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2006.001, 2006.008, and NPA.2006.098.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically. The files are grouped into two series:
Missing Title
Papers
Photographs
Historical/Biographical Note
Hermina ("Hermie") Dumont Huiswoud (1905-1998), was born in British Guiana (now Guyana), and migrated to New York in 1919. In 1926 she married Otto Eduard Huiswoud (1893-1961), born in Dutch Guiana (now Surinam) and a charter member of the Communist Party of the United States of America. Otto was also active in international communist activities, including heading the Profintern's International Trade Union Committee of Negro Workers, and editing their publication, The Negro Worker, under the name Charles Woodson. Hermina accompanied her husband to Moscow, Paris, Antwerp and Amsterdam, where she settled in 1949. She actively participated in activities associated with the Left, and wrote articles for radical publications. Langston Hughes was one of her friends and correspondents.
Sources:
Turner, Joyce Moore. Caribbean Crusaders and the Harlem Renaissance (Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 2005)
Custodial History
Hermina Dumont Huiswoud gave this collection of her papers and correspondence to her biographer Joyce Moore Turner.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains Hermina Huiswoud's correspondence with friends, postcards, letters from Otto, correspondence regarding Otto (most with academic researchers), 46 letters and postcards from Langston Hughes, "Ballad of the Brown King: A Christmas Cantata" by Hughes; Hermina's newspaper articles, literary manuscripts, and biographical sketches of Otto; articles by Otto, and personal documents for both Otto and Hermina (citizenship, passports, pension, work, etc.), biographical materials relating to relatives; and biographical materials and correspondence relating to the Burroughs family (African American radicals). Also included in the collection are photographs of Hermina and Otto Huiswoud and of their travels in the Caribbean.
Photographs.; Postcards.; Manuscripts; Communism.; International communist activities.; African American communists.; Personalia.; Correspondence.; Burroughs, Charles; Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967; Red International of Labor Unions; Communist Party of the United States of America; Communist International; Huiswoud, Otto; Turner, Joyce Moore, 1920-
- Series I: Papers
  - Burroughs Family (African American Radicals) - Clippings, circa 1946-1990s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Burroughs Family (African American Radicals) - Correspondence, 1973, 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence (H.H.), 1966-1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence (H.H.) - Postcards, 1972-1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence (Otto Huiswoud to H.H.), 1942-1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence re Otto Huiswoud, 1961-1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence - Researchers re Otto Huiswoud, 1962-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence - U.S. Citizenship Status (H.H.), 1951-1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Council on African Affairs (re United Nations Charter and Colonialism), 1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Famiri [?] - Articles for O.H. on Cuba, Pushkin, etc., Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Guyana, 1953-1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hughes, Langston - Ballad of the Brown King: A Christmas Cantata, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Hughes, Langston - Commemorative Material, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hughes, Langston - Commemorative Postcards, 1938-1989 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Hughes, Langston - Letters (2) to Hermina Huiswoud, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Hughes, Langston - Letters (13) to Hermina Huiswoud, 1938-1949 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Hughes, Langston - Letters (5) to Hermina Huiswoud, 1950-1957 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Hughes, Langston - Letters (10) to Hermina Huiswoud, 1961-1967 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Hughes, Langston: Postcards (16) to Hermina Huiswoud, circa 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Huiswoud, Christian (1895-1941), 1970-1984 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Huiswoud, Ricardo, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Negro Question, Red International of Labor Unions - Otto Huiswoud, George Padmore Articles, 1928-1930 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Negro Worker- Otto Huiswoud Articles, 1931-1935 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Newspaper Articles (H.H.) in Dutch, English, Undated, 1930-1943 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Otto Eduard Huiswoud: Early Years and Political Parties / by H.H., Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Personal Documents (H.H., O.H.) - Citizenship, Death, Marriage, Passports, Pension, Work (I), circa 1890-1960s (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Personal Documents (H.H., O.H.) - Citizenship, Death, Marriage, Passports, Pension, Work (II), ca. 1890-1960s (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Personal Documents (H.H., O.H.) - Citizenship, Death, Marriage, Passports, Pension, Work (III), circa 1890-1960s (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Pool, Rosie, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Postcards, Blank (folder 1), Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Postcards, Blank (folder 2), Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Robeson, Paul - Stamp Campaign, Undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Stove Invention (O.H.), Undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Treaty with Bush Negroes in Suriname (translated by H.H.), Undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Women, Biographical Essays on ("Women I Have Known Personally"), Undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Writings (H.H.) - Plays, Poetry, Stories, Undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Writings, Third Party, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Series II: Photographs
  - Cuba Photographs, 1946 (Box Tamiment Shared A003, Folder 7)
  - Hermina Huiswoud Family Photographs, circa 1890-1910 (Box Tamiment Shared A003, Folder 8)
  - Otto Huiswoud Family Photographs, circa 1907-1977 (Box Tamiment Shared A003, Folder 9)
  - Otto Huiswoud Photographs and Postcards, circa 1940-1960 (Box Tamiment Shared A003, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, circa 1960-1980 (Box Tamiment Shared A003, Folder 11)